<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2028</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Nick Malik]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://blogs.msdn.com/nickmalik</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>131.107.0.102</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2008-02-11 19:07:17</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2008-02-12 03:07:17</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I was at the Obama political rally on Friday.  Here's the thing:
His campaign announces that there will be a rally at the Key Arena (where the Seattle Supersonics Pro Basketball team plays) on Wednesday.  Not a big announcement.  No advertising.  No radio and TV spots.  Free press only.

By Friday morning, at 11am, there was a line around the block to get into Key Arena.  After filling the place to capacity (17,000 people), they had to close the doors.  Fire code.

5,000 more people stood outside, in the cold, and waited for three hours.  When Barak came, we heard him on loud speakers.  

Harry: I canvassed for Bill Clinton (twice) and John Kerry as well.  I knocked on doors and attended rallys and stood on street corners reminding voters to Get Out and Vote.  I placed signs and hung banners and, yes, attended rallys.

Most rallys have about 100 people.  Really Big Rallys can draw 1,000 people.

22,000 people is not a rally.  22,000 people, with no advertising, and two day's notice, in a far-away corner of the country, not used to getting any political attention at all... that's historic.

Hillary drew 5,000 on the same day, a few hours earlier.

The fact that she lost by ONLY 2-to-1 in the polls shows that her voters get to the polls far more than they get to the rallys.  

But she lost.  Big.

I like them both.  Either would make a fine president.  But I'm rooting for Barak.  ]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>