<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2031</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Dale Churchward]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>dale.churchward@microsoft.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://halfmybrain.spaces.live.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>131.107.0.102</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2008-02-19 11:27:07</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2008-02-19 19:27:07</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Harry and I come from opposite sides of the political spectrum, but one thing I can say for sure, he is not an idiot. I find it interesting to discuss politics with Harry as he makes me think about why I support certain politicans and issues. While we often disagree I always respect the thought process that led him to the views he takes.

Also, it is hard for me to accept calling him a bigot. No matter the reason, Harry will likely support either Hillary Clinton or Barak Obama. That in itself should point out that he is not a bigot. As far as him comments about Mitt Romney, they might of been a bit strong, although it was pretty well known that the other candidates for the Republican nomination couldn't stand Mitt. I am LDS, just like Mitt, and I have never felt Harry has treated me any differently then any of his other co-workers. He has even asked me questions about the church, and has not treated me any different because of my religious beliefs.

In any case, this is Harry's blog. He writes about technology much of the time because he is passionate about it, but he also writes about other areas that interest him such as hockey, movies, and politics. We make the choice to read his thoughts or now, but I will say Harry does a good job tagging his blog entires so you can decide if you wish to read them or not.]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>