<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2448</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Don Smith]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>dons@microsoft.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://blogs.msdn.com/donsmith</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>131.107.0.102</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2007-01-31 11:39:42</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2007-01-31 19:39:42</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[It's interesting that you took the developer perspective Harry. I can see how a real proficient dev who has memorized all the necessary WCF attributes and config sections might just choose to write the code instead of invoke wizards. Most of these recipes certainly aren't generating mind-bending code ... actually they are generating mind-numbing code. It isn't interesting code to write and certainly not fun. The exception might be the code generated by the data access guidance package - this stuff is more interesting, but there sure can be a lot of it ... but is data access the problem we want to go solve ... again? :)

I'm surprised you didn't take the architect perspective. What about the ability to modify the guidance packages to include the architectural or policy decisions of the solutions? I know it isn't super easy, but it's more interesting than writing property assessors :) I would think the ability to define new code analysis rules interesting to architects too.

I'll check into disabling recipes from being shown in the guidance navigator window. I'm almost positive there is a way to do this. I'll ping you offline. 

I'll also have someone ping you about the x.509 and kerb issues you ran into. We don't have any known issues around these recipes so I'm interested in what caused them.

As always, thanks for the feedback and insight!]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>