<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>3002</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Me]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP></wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2004-02-27 07:04:39</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2004-02-27 15:04:39</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I think you need to see the bigger issue. Gay marriage isn't about two consenting adults making a decisions and we should let them alone and do what they want. It is a societal issue. Those in favor of gay marriage say it is so they can enjoy the same benefits that heterosexual couples have. Where does it lead to? For example, if gay marriage is becomes accepted by society "made legal", then if a gay couple decides to become married, are churches then required to perform the ceremony? No, then why are churches even needed anymore to perform a marriage. Why even is marriage needed? As I look at this issue I see this more being about one section of society looking for acceptance, and the removal of the guilt they feel about their act than benefits. No one wants to feel guilt, why is there guilt at all. Mainly because an individual feels there is a higher being or higher thing that holds them responsible for what they do. If you remove this from the equation, by slowly tearing down a person's religious beliefs, you lose the guilt. Eventually remove the religion from the equation. Take out "In God we Trust", take out anything that would be implied as sinful so people don't have to feel guilt. Ask yourself, if gay marriage is ok (even though biblically it isn't), then why isn't poligamy ok? I hear people say "Why that would be immoral!". Who or what then defines morality? How can morality say one thing is ok and another wrong. Eventually morality doesn't matter anymore to a society. Whether or not you or anyone else likes it, we currently have a majority of the population who believe in a higher being, and being a western society they base this belief on the bible. Whether you're Jewish, Islam, or Christian, they all hold a belief in the Old Testament, which is what is basing the moral belief on marriage being between a man and woman. You cannot pick and chose morality from what a society is based on. All great civilizations eventually fall from within, and the commonality of it is when the people of a society no longer have a common belief system. Whether this is due to a conquering force integrating different cultures and nothing cohesive holds the society together, or a new and upcoming religion makes the existing system fall. This is where the country is headed the eventual of a belief system and subsequently the society itself.]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>