<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2836</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[David Ing]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>david.ing@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://from9till2.com</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>81.151.37.56</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2005-09-03 13:45:29</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2005-09-03 20:45:29</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I personally prefer the term Architect to be used more like a 'role' than a 'job'. In some (surprisingly very rare) cases it *may* be possible that what you are doing is so very complex that one person takes on that remit as their single and dedicated 'role'. Even then though, due to title inflation, they tend to often make the mistake of not participating in the team with other useful role slices; and then flounder in an alternative reality to the one that actually ships working stuff. 

This is actually odd, as a developer's 'test' their code, even with a dedicated test engineer around, but that doesn't stop them being called a 'developer'; just as TE's do develop lots of code. 

Architects (as a job title) smooze, spec, design, code, test, juggle and can sweep the floor with a party trick involving a broom - it's just an awkward name given to people with a wide remit and depth of experience, and is probably more of a memed organizational positioning term rather than a concrete job description, i.e. L61.

Now, if it is all about positioning and seniority levels then I propose just delisting the word 'architect', call us all 'developers' and then find a suitably horrible word set for people with less experience. About 500 years ago we had 'Serf, Lord, Baron, King' - worth a go again? Would make a great org chart? ;-)

- David (Serf)
]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>