<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<item>
  <title>Preparing to Present in Beijing</title>
  <link>http://devhawk.net/2004/09/17/preparing-to-present-in-beijing/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2004 16:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">devhawk</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://b4e7e5c6-6ca7-40e2-baf2-a91fa93b6219</guid>
  <description></description>
  <content:encoded xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><![CDATA[<p>I made it to Beijing yesterday with no problem. There was a car waiting for me at the airport, and one of the speaker managers met me at my hotel shortly after I arrived. They even provide a loner <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsmobile/devices/devicedisplay.aspx?module=deviceDisplay;Smartphone;apac;58">dopod SmartPhone</a> for use while I'm here though I'm not sure who I would call. I went to the attendee dinner last night and on to a party for local partners. I spoke to a few people, including a gentleman from <a href="http://digitalchina.com/">Digital China</a> who reads my blog. It's nice to be recognized at all, much less as an <a href="http://devhawk.net/PermaLink.aspx?guid=52945d4e-bc1a-496c-b3f3-195e5ca416f5">International Man of Architecture</a>.</p><p>After dinner, I worked for an hour or so with the translator for my Metropolis session, Quanzhan. Quanzhan is from China, but he's now a program manager in the Windows Server division at corp - his office is just on the other side of campus. He's here doing presentations of his own as well as helping out as a translator. I've met at least one other Chinese person here who works in Redmond - I'm guessing presenting TechEd China provides a great way for these folks to visit home and also give back to the community they are from in some way. </p><p>Delivering these presentations via a translator will be an interesting challenge. I've never worked thru a translator before. Each session has it's own unique challenge - Data in SOA is very technical while Metropolis is pretty abstract. I ended up cutting 20 slides from today's Metropolis talk in order to ensure I have enough time to hit the important points. Presenting this way requires a truly conservative approach to word choice - even though my session is 75 minutes long, in reality I have closer to 30 as everything I say has to be spoken twice. I'm grateful that Quanzhan and I spent the time last night going thru the presentation even though we were both exhausted. I guess we'll see how well the session goes today, but I think we'll do well.</p>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">439</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2004-09-17 16:20:35</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2004-09-17 16:20:35</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">preparing-to-present-in-beijing</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"></wp:post_password>
  <wp:is_sticky xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="architecture"><![CDATA[Architecture]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_entryid</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[b4e7e5c6-6ca7-40e2-baf2-a91fa93b6219]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitle</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Preparing+To+Present+In+Beijing]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitleunique</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2004/09/17/Preparing+To+Present+In+Beijing]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
</item>