<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2373</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Julianne Pierson]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>juliannepierson@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://techiewife</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>24.16.92.194</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2006-06-22 11:33:51</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2006-06-22 18:33:51</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Here is the thing, we ask SO much of our teachers and we teachers get such a crap load of disrespect for trying to do the right thing. I tried to teach my students to think, you see, how they solved a problem was most often times more important than the answer they came to. If I could teach them how to problem solve, I would have taught them how to think. In teaching them how to think, I believe that I helped them realize their individuality. In so doing I most definately was NOT creating factory workers (not that there is anything wrong with becoming one) the important thing I was teaching was the power of choice. The power of thought. The power of their brains. Still, our country has asked teachers to become parents, social workers, educators, doctors, nutritionists, social commentators and reporters all at the same time...oh yes all the while paying less to the teachers then we do the bus drivers. I am not kidding the teachers in most systems are paid less than bus drivers it is a travesty. I am still not convinces home schooling is the answer either as so much social integration is lost. Perhaps, as I have suggested to my husband, school systems should enable partial home school, partial school house school (some already do this) but in order for that to work, parents who stay at home to educate, rear and nurture their kids need resources, tools and education (not to mention more tax breaks since they do not get an income...wouldnt it be great if stay at home parents who could prove that they were raising kids got a special tax break to make that more financially possible in an age when two income families are a necessity not a choice??) anyway obviously this strikes a chord with me, the old social worker/teacher who is now a stay at home Mom of two...]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>