<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2546</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Chris May]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>chris@christophermayinc.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://www.chrismay.org</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>208.18.167.6</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2007-07-05 07:58:44</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2007-07-05 14:58:44</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[The BS about how many people Clinton pardoned is a red herring for many reasons, but mainly for these:

1) Bush's commutation of Libby's sentence has nothing to do with the facts of the case and everything to do with cronyism and that Libby was taking the fall for Cheney/Bush on this matter.

2) Bush's commutation of Libby's sentence goes against his OWN stated policies for dealing with pardons and commutation requests.

3) Bush has pardoned/commuted almost no one during his time as our President.  This futher illustrates how far outside of normal operation he was willing to go to let his friend off the hook.

4) You keep bringing up Clinton.  For this exact same crime, Clinton was impeached, and was kicked off the bar.  So the same people who screamed from the rafters that perjury was enough of a crime to remove the president, are now the same people who say it isn't enough of a crime to spend 1 day in jail.

5) Clinton's impeachment was based on a civil case where he lied about his personal life and affairs.  Libby leaked the name of an undercover operative (later deemed NOT a crime because Bush/Cheney authorized it), but then lied to cover up his, and Cheney's involvement.

6) The idea that Scooter got 2 years in jail because he "forgot some stuff" is ludicrous.  Not only was the (conservative) prosecutor absolutely convinced that Libby intentionally lied in an effort to obstuct justice.  When presented with the evidence the jury had no problem coming to a unanimous guilty verdict, and the Judge agreed with them when he imposed the sentence.  Or are you going to defend Clinton because he "forgot some stuff".  Lame!

7) Most importantly, the "B-b-b-but Clinton..." defense is stupid.  If Clinton did something shady, that doesn't mean it's fine and dandy for a Republican to do the same, EXPICALLY after chastising him for years on the topic.  

]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>