<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2547</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Chris]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>chris@dscoduc.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>64.156.199.117</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2007-07-05 11:44:19</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2007-07-05 18:44:19</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[You can feel free to think it's a red herring but I beleive we are talking apples to apples...

Okay, lets deal with these one at a time...

1.)  Bush has stated that he beleived the punishment was excessive - the same reason given by Bill Clinton.  So Bill thinks that prison is excessive for a bank robber and no one complains about that, but Bush thinks that libby's punishment for lying is excessive and now all of a sudden it's outrageous.  Nice.

2.) The Democrats have tried to pin Bush down to saying that he will hold anyone accountable for their crimes.  That's a nice strategy to use to try and force the President to not be able to do 'what he believes' is the right thing.  Again, pardons are given to the president for his discression.  If you don't like right, or think that Presidents abuse it then vote to change that right.  The difference between Republicans and Democrats is that Republicans just scratch their head and say whatever, where as the Democrats cry and moan about it.

3.)  You call releasing Libby from 30 months as "off the hook" but forget to mention the remaining fines and probation that Libby is still required to account for.  I disagree that Libby is off the hook.

4.) I keep bringing up Clinton exactly because of the Democrats double standard.  All during the impeachment trials all I ever heard was how Clinton didn't do anything wrong.  Even if I can get over the fact that he disgraced the office by getting a B-job by an intern in the Oval Office, I still can't get past the video of Clinton saying "I did not have sexual relations with that woman".  So yes, he was impeached for lying to the court, and should have REMOVED HIMSELF as President.  In the end it was never even discussed to have Clinton spend 1 day in jail for the same crime you seem to think Libby should spend 30 months in jail for committing.

5.) This is the best part of the story.  An invistigation is created to look into a possible crime.  Testimony is taken for what is later discovered to be not a crime.  Then someone is convicted for lying about something during the testimony of the "non-crime".  That process happens over and over by both parties in an effort to catch anyone saying something that wasn't true.  The whole thing is a joke, on both sides.

6.) Libby was convicted of lying but always maintained that he didn't recall what was said in his conversations:  "The prosecution alleges that Libby deliberately misled FBI agents and a grand jury about several conversations he had with journalists then. Defense lawyers contend their client was too busy to recall the details of those conversations."  (http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/16/AR2007011600145.html).  That is the basis of my comment that he "forgot some stuff".  Clinton would have a hard time convincing me that he didn't remember having sexual relations with Monica when he spoke directly to me (the public) on the television.

7.) This whole discussion is more about the hiprocracy of the Democrats and not that Libby was wrongly convicted.  In the end it doesn't matter because Bush had every right to pardon Libby for any reason he saw fit.  Again, if you don't like it then you should try and change the law, not cry about how corrupt this administration is, and not mention how corrupt the Clinton administration was.

My impression of all politicians is that they are basically untrustworthy, both Republicans and Democrats.  Something about absolute power corrupting absolutely.  But even with that said I get sick and tired of hearing about 'how unfathomably corrupt' this administration is from the Democrats.  It's like the Democrats spent the Clinton times with their heads in the sand...

Case in point:
- http://prorev.com/hillary.htm
- http://www.realchange.org/clinton.htm
- http://www.greaterthings.com/News/Clinton_Scandals/index.html
]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>