<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2698</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[brant]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>brantcarter@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP></wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2004-10-27 07:27:31</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2004-10-27 14:27:31</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[There was a big difference between Kay's lecture and the keynote that I don't think you are capturing.

- The product demo during the Keynote was delivered by the Program Manager for the tool; not from the primary speaker (Head of MS Research)

- The product demo was very hard to follow and didn't seem to re-enforce any of the topics that the speaker had let up to; it felt very disconnected: hence the commercial feel to it

- Kay's lecture was really his business; the lecture is the reward he gets for all the great contributions he has made during his career; if he wan't to show some products that's his choice.  A Keynote is different; its supposed to setup the theme of the conference: there are plenty of other times during the conference for product demos

- Kay's demo wasn't really pushing a vendor or a product; but rather (IMO) trying to show the lack of innovation in computing science; this fit very well with his entire lecture which was positioned as a challenge to the community to teach better, and innovate more.  (BTW: it is clear that he views MS as one of the companies NOT innovating I would be interested to see you blog about that)

I saw MANY people just walk out during the MS Keynote demo it was clear that
- Many (more than 50%) were Java developers that really have no use for MS only tools
- Many felt it inappropriate to be doing a product demo at that time
- MS "abused" its priviledge of the Keynote by resorting to blatant produt advertising

cheers

b

PS: One my Day 1 highlights was Ward Cunningham's lecture did you attend that?]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>