<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2210</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Ruiyi Zhang]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>ruiyizhang@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>158.106.48.10</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2009-05-18 19:52:00</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2009-05-19 02:52:00</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[You may want to listen to the latest Herding Code episode interviewing DotNetNuke co-founder Joe Brinkman (http://herdingcode.com/?p=183). Even though the main topic is about webforms vs asp.net mvc. Towards the end of the show, he did address his experiences and thoughts on maintaining a large-scale open source project.

To summarize his ideas around the issues of accepting community contributions in large scale open source projects backed by commercial companies:

* Community contributions are generally welcomed, or even begged, when a project is small.
* When project grows bigger, the cost and risk of accepting community contributions become prohibitively high.
* A community contributor usually doesn't have the big picture of the project in mind when he/she contributes his/her patches.

This is really a poor summary (mainly due to my broken English) of the things discussed in the show. So be sure to listen to the original podcast.

To make your presentation more interesting than political rallies, I believe it will do more impact if you could focus the presentation on proposing some constructive resolutions to the many known hurdles a commercial company backed open source project faces in accepting community contributions. After all, the Internet doesn't lack blank arguments of urging Microsoft to be more open.]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>