<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2212</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Kevin Gregg]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>kevin@infination.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://infination.info/contacts</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>70.157.7.197</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2009-05-19 02:53:32</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2009-05-19 09:53:32</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[After 30 years of profit, making (at one point) Bill Gates not only the richest man in America, but also personally owning 40% of the US GDP.  I'd say it's time to give back in a big, big way.  Not to the stockholders.  It's time to go back to grassroots, streamlined, security-minded coding--pure interoperability--where the focus is not on how much profit can be milked out of a proprietary sale of a technology solution, but rather everyone on the same page and working together to solve the issues that IT faces today.  No arguments; a good product will make the developer profit from his hard work.  It's time to take the venom out of the proprietary code and ensure that all pieces of code written work seamlessly on all platforms.  The days of narrow-minded, one-dimensional operating system software should have already been behind us as an IT community. Let's embrace the opportunities we have to collaborate and make software work for our nations, our states, and our cities.  The future has been now for over a decade and a half, and yet another development of a new OS is a tired idea.  Let's improve the ones we have, all work to make our days go by better, and a sense of pride and honor and integrity will increase the morale of the IT community at-large.  

KG
Network Security Research Analyst
Infination Technology Research
kevin@infination.com
662.497.2890
http://infination.info/contacts]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>