<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<item>
  <title>T-Mobile Rocks, Sprint Sucks</title>
  <link>http://devhawk.net/2004/08/22/t-mobile-rocks-sprint-sucks/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2004 21:10:31 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">devhawk</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://ac168f48-6765-4e23-8521-27fc633c568c</guid>
  <description></description>
  <content:encoded xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><![CDATA[<p>A while ago, <a href="http://conpro.net/">Tom</a><a href="http://www.conpro.net/PermaLink.aspx?guid=558f432f-3118-4ad2-ba50-b3476a8849b6">mentioned</a> that I had a great customer service experience with T-Mobile. Truthfully, the great customer service experience came today. T-Mobile just earned a customer for...well, maybe not for life, but they certainly have earned enough karma to keep me around a while. And at the same time, Sprint has spurned a customer for life. </p><p>I <a href="http://devhawk.net/PermaLink.aspx?guid=75f886b0-06db-4cf1-9534-604a518841f8">blogged</a> back in April about getting a SmartPhone. Well, the honeymoon was short lived - it was a developer beta unit and it was not particularly robust. I dropped it about a month ago and it died. No huge deal, the <a href="http://www.motorola.com/motoinfo/product/details/0,,53,00.html">MPx220</a> is coming soon. Of course, I need a phone in the meantime. I had signed up for T-Mobile service to power the SmartPhone so I went back to pick up a <a href="http://www.motorola.com/mdirect/hellomoto/experience/v300/flash/index.shtml">V300</a> which would go to my wife when the MPx220 became available. Only trouble was that since I hadn't bought the phone when I activated my account, I was not eligible for an activation discount. I had asked about that when I bought the service, and had been assured it was no big deal. So I call up customer service, and they promise to wave the disconnect fee on the current account if I buy a new phone (with the activation discount). This was right before I went to New Zealand, so I figured I'd take care of it when I got back. In the meantime, I'm using a old borrowed phone and my existing account.</p><p>So I've been back a week, but hadn't gotten to taking care of the phone yet. Then last night, someone steals my phone and my wife's phone out of the car. So I call T-Mobile and explain the situation. They cancel the account on the spot, outright - no early termination fee or anything. Pretty cool. Of course, I did tell them I was going to buy not one but two new <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/stores/detail/-/wireless/B0000WZWSI/ref=w_zr_hp_td_blah2/002-7066890-6721622">V300's from Amazon</a> (for the low price of -$100 each after rebate) but still, I thought that was pretty cool. The only bummer of this whole scenario is that I won't be able to get the MPx220 with an activation discount when it comes up.</p><p>After talking to T-Mobile, I called Sprint. Now, I've been a Sprint customer for five years. You would think that would warrant a little respect and/or leeway, but apparently not. The "customer service" rep I spoke to was both rude and stupid. He was able to suspend my wife's phone, but when I asked to cancel it he told me there would be an early termination fee. Funny thing is, the term on this "contract" (which I never signed and was unaware of) end's on the 28th of August. You know, next Saturday. As in, six days from today. You would think that you might give a customer of five years who is dealing with a case of theft the benefit of the doubt and wave the early termination fee less than a week before the contract expires anyway. No, apparently I have to call back Saturday to terminate the contract. Fine. I set a reminder on my calendar so I don't forget to rid myself of Sprint for good and forever. </p>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">425</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2004-08-22 21:10:31</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2004-08-22 21:10:31</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">t-mobile-rocks-sprint-sucks</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"></wp:post_password>
  <wp:is_sticky xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="general-geekery"><![CDATA[General Geekery]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_entryid</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[ac168f48-6765-4e23-8521-27fc633c568c]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitle</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[TMobile+Rocks+Sprint+Sucks]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitleunique</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2004/08/23/TMobile+Rocks+Sprint+Sucks]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:comment_id>2670</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Chris Church]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP></wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2004-08-23 20:47:46</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2004-08-24 03:47:46</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Its a shame the wireless companies each seem to have a major flaw.  I switched from AT&T (after 10 years) to Nextel 'cause my new job issued me one.  What a mistake - the radio service severely sucks, and I get dropped calls on the cell all the time.  I saw a Gartner "magic quadrant" on the cell carriers about a year ago and it was surprising how mediocre to crappy they all were in at least one major dimension.  The trouble is - they all seem to be crappy at something different!]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
  </wp:comment>
</item>