<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<item>
  <title>Thoughts on Election Day</title>
  <link>http://devhawk.net/2006/11/10/thoughts-on-election-day/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2006 11:48:46 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">devhawk</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://6fe9af1f-e0ed-46bf-88f6-60bc04cc8a9c</guid>
  <description></description>
  <content:encoded xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><![CDATA[<p>I've had a few days to savor the Democrat landslide victory this past Tuesday. I was half right about the razor thin majorities. Democrats have a slim two seat advantage in the senate, but a fairly significant thirty-four seat majority in the house (with ten races undecided). Given that the Republicans had a twenty-eight seat majority in the last congress, that's a pretty significant turnaround for the Democrats. Frankly, I'm pretty excited. </p><p>Here are a few short takes on the election: </p><ul><li>We can close the book on Rove's "permanent republican majority" pipe dream. America isn't a conservative country. It isn't a liberal country, either. It's a moderate country. Liberal and conservative are the words we use to describe the direction one diverges from the middle ground. This election was decided by the moderates in this country, which isn't surprising as the bell curve tells us that it's the moderates who are in the majority. Political parties ignore the middle at their own peril.  </li><li>Democrats didn't win the election on Tuesday, the Republicans lost it. Hard working moderate Americans have limited tolerance for ineptitude and corruption, as the Democrats found out in '94 and the Republicans found out this week. There are those on the left howling for elephant blood, but spending time exacting revenge on the Republicans won't solve any of America's hard problems. The Democrats are <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/cq/2006/11/08/cq_1916.html?adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1163144214-/6a4nq4LqOgJNehwFIBMbw">talking like they realize this</a>, but actions speak louder than words.  </li><li>Speaking of actions and words, President Bush <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/news/releases/2006/11/20061108-2.html">talked a good talk</a> Wednesday, but I'll believe President "<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bushism">The Decider</a>" Bush honestly wants to "work with the new Congress in a bipartisan way" when I see it. Trying to push <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/11/09/bolton.congress/index.html">John Bolton's confirmation</a> as well as retroactive authorization for the warrantless wiretapping program through congress before Democrats officially take control isn't a promising start.  </li><li>There's no such thing as a political party that actively works for limited government. It isn't that surprising, as it violates my <a href="http://devhawk.net/2006/10/03/Numero+Uno+Theory+Of+Sociology.aspx">Numero Uno</a> theory. Individuals may want limited government, but there's no way a government entity like a political party will actively work to reduce their own importance. Republicans claim to be for shrinking the federal government, but their actions contradict that claim. Republicans like Reagan and Bush cut taxes, but they never actually cut spending to match. As such, the <a href="http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/7794/428/1600/a1.28.jpg">Federal Debt / GDP ratio</a> has about doubled in the past 18 years, with the only reduction coming while Clinton was in office. Claiming to cut taxes without cutting spending is like claiming you're making more money because you're not paying your mortgage. Republicans aren't cutting taxes, they're deferring them. It's time to realize that you can't <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starve_the_beast">starve the beast</a> and move on to more pragmatic policies. Better a tax-and-spend liberal than a borrow-and-spend conservative.</li></ul><p>Update: In the interest of bipartisanship, <a href="http://www.tpmmuckraker.com/archives/001981.php">here are some less than reputable Democrats</a> poised to take key positions in the new Democrat controlled congress. Making someone with a <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/campaigns/junkie/links/hastings102189.htm">congressional impeachment</a> or <a href="http://www.tpmmuckraker.com/archives/000502.php">under FBI investigation</a> the chair of a congressional committee isn't a promising start to "<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/06/AR2006100600602.html">draining the swamp</a>". </p>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">830</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2006-11-10 11:48:46</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2006-11-10 11:48:46</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">thoughts-on-election-day</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"></wp:post_password>
  <wp:is_sticky xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="category" nicename="politics"><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitleunique</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2006/11/10/Thoughts+On+Election+Day]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitle</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Thoughts+On+Election+Day]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_entryid</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[6fe9af1f-e0ed-46bf-88f6-60bc04cc8a9c]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:comment_id>2432</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[MinorRipper]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>mikedidier@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url>http://www.minor-ripper.blogspot.com</wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>66.9.26.10</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2006-11-10 11:59:39</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2006-11-10 19:59:39</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I think it's appropriate that we get underway in relegating the Bush Jr. foreign policy team into the dustbin of history ASAP after the election --Rumsfeld, Bolton, Cheney (hopefully). Doesn't the whole 'neocon' era already seem like a bad nightmare??  Never again.  Yeah right!

www.minor-ripper.blogspot.com]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
  </wp:comment>
  <wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:comment_id>2433</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Libertarian]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>72.201.155.147</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2006-11-10 12:17:38</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2006-11-10 20:17:38</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Interestingly enough, I agree with pretty much everything you wrote. It will be interesting to see in 2 years if progress has been made, or more excuses. Believing Bush to cooperate when you see it may be entirely appropriate; however, I'm a little more optimistic based on his history as TX governor working with democrats. If you think about it, before the election he wasn't working with democrats at all. Heck, he wasn't even working with republicans! At the very least this election sends a loud message all politicians, and I think that is definitely a good thing.]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
  </wp:comment>
  <wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:comment_id>2434</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Dale Churchward]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>dale.churchward@microsoft.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url>http://halfmybrain.spaces.live.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>131.107.0.102</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2006-11-13 11:04:47</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2006-11-13 19:04:47</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[As much as I hate to admit it, I agree with a lot of what you wrote Harry, especially about the Republicans being fired. As far as Bush pushing through stuff before the new Congressional session I can't blame him for that. Is he really just supposed to wait until January when it will be much harder? That really wouldn't be the smartest move on his part.

As far as the Democrats cleaning house and not tolerating the corruption of the Republican I found an article I thought was really interesting.
 
http://www.rollcall.com/issues/1_1/breakingnews/15974-1.html

It sure looks like the Democrats aren’t embracing the concept of draining the swamp. Not that I expected them to. Politicians are politicians no matter the party and they seem to like to defend their own.
]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
  </wp:comment>
</item>