<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2594</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Tom Vande Stouwe, MCT, MCSD]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>tomv@conpro.net</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://www.conpro.net</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP></wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2004-05-11 13:41:06</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2004-05-11 20:41:06</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[While I agree with Darrel on the numbrer of 'small' companies, I disagree with the conclusion. While these companies have low scalability need now, as the quantity and quality og 'network enabled applications' and the use of Web Services et al, will make scalability and reusability very important topics for the small enterprise.

large organizations are already architecting to scale, but the small company is ignoring it, and they will be the ones that will get caught short. We live in a global economy, and the well connected mud hut in lower Slobinia will take business from Main Street if they present a better electronic face.

My Conclusion? Architecting and scalability is MORE important to the under 100 member comnpanies then to the Fortune 100 companies.  The fact that this represents 90% of American companies just points to the importance to our National economy not to ignore these 'not so low hanging fruit' companies. 

We need to look at small company architecture as more of a structured approach, where processes will more likely impact the companies processes then in big companies where we try to make the systems work like the users, rather then the other way around. We need to start looking at Small enterprises as nothing more then small node on the larger network, and position ourselves and our clients to capitalize on that.

In any case we can be sure that the needs of our small business will be met, either by us, or by our (international and national) competition.]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>