<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2843</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Larry O'Brien]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>lobrien@email.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url>http://www.knowing.net/</wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>66.8.188.164</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2005-09-08 12:26:21</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2005-09-08 19:26:21</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Your point is a good one, but it's harmed by your choice of Java as an example. If you chose server-side development as your benchmark, Java would come out ahead of VB in adoption. Meanwhile, your point on the relationship between productivity, performance, and abstraction is strengthened when memory management is taken as the subject: is the abstraction of managed memory a productivity boost? Absolutely. Is it lower in performance? Yes, when compared to a skilled developer. 

Saying that Java is/was primarily competitive with VB is too revisionist. Java came out at the beginning of the massive wave of server-side / Web development and crushed C++ and Perl as the preferred environment for that type of programming. Java's original APIs included network and threading libraries that were both easier than any others and standardized, creating a perfect little ecosystem of programmers, educators, and business people, all eager to move into this new realm. 

At that point, server-side portability _was_ important because business people _did not know_ if Microsoft would deliver a stable and scalable server OS. In the mid-to-late 90s, hedging your bets over server-side OS choice was a good decision from both a business and technical perspective.

Now, that's no longer an issue and part of the reason that .NET has more momentum than Java is precisely because the /. crowd is the only one left that thinks that MS hasn't proved itself on the server. ]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>