<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<item>
  <title>Morning Coffee 150</title>
  <link>http://devhawk.net/2008/02/27/morning-coffee-150/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2008 18:17:22 +0000</pubDate>
  <dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">devhawk</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://5f0a893b-18d0-4e4c-9383-d53fb532b8f3</guid>
  <description></description>
  <content:encoded xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><![CDATA[<ul><li>Yesterday was the NHL trading deadline, and the Capitals were very busy. They obtained <a href="http://capitals.nhl.com/team/app/?service=page&amp;page=NewsPage&amp;articleid=354907">Huet from Montreal</a>, <a href="http://capitals.nhl.com/team/app/?service=page&amp;page=NewsPage&amp;articleid=354946">Federov from Columbus</a> and <a href="http://capitals.nhl.com/team/app/?service=page&amp;page=NewsPage&amp;articleid=354952">Cooke from Vancouver</a>. Given they are fighting just to make the playoffs, going for three soon-to-be unrestricted free agents seems like an odd choice. However, the consensus (among my parents anyway) was that it's critical to get this very young Caps team some playoff experience. Even if all three walk at season's end, it'll be worth if the Caps make a playoff run. Besides it's not like we gave up much: an extra second round pick in '09, a <a href="http://und.cstv.com/sports/m-hockey/mtt/ruth_teddy00.html">19 year old defensive prospect</a> (who was apparently <em>14th </em>on the depth chart) and an <a href="http://sports.espn.go.com/nhl/players/profile?playerId=724">underachieving winger</a>.  </li><li>Speaking of the Caps playoff chances, they are currently one and a half games back of the division leading Hurricanes and two games behind the current eighth seed Flyers. Yes, I rank hockey teams using baseball's standings system. Otherwise, you have to talk about games in hand (i.e. the Caps are five points behind Carolina with two games in hand).  </li><li>The writer's guild <a href="http://unitedhollywood.blogspot.com/2008/02/strike-officially-over-contract.html">ratified the new contract</a>, so Hollywood labor strife is now officially behind us. At least until July when the the actors may go on strike.  </li><li>It seems like a slow week for Microsoft geek news, which is odd since WS08, VS08 and SQL08 all <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/heroeshappenhere/default.mspx">launch today</a>. I'm guessing it's the calm before the <a href="http://www.visitmix.com/">Mix</a> storm next week.  </li><li>After <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/xmlteam/archive/2007/06/05/linq-to-xsd-preview-alpha-0-2-to-go-with-orcas-beta-1.aspx">going dark</a> for six months, <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/xmlteam/archive/2008/02/21/linq-to-xsd-alpha-0-2.aspx">Linq to XSD</a> has been re-released to work with the RTM version of VS08. Scott Hanselman <a href="http://www.hanselman.com/blog/LINQToEverythingLINQToXSDAddsMoreLINQiness.aspx">demonstrates</a> Linq to XSD by applying it to <a href="http://www.ofx.org/">OFX</a>, an XML Schema he calls "goofy" but apparently helped develop. OFX uses <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#derivation-by-restriction">derivation by restriction</a>, which has no direct corollary in C#, but Linq to XSD's  is able to translate between XML and objects without loosing any of that type fidelity. Nice to know Linq to XSD can tolerate OFX's level of goofiness, though I'm guessing most people use much more straightforward schemas.  </li><li>Speaking of Linq, I discovered <a href="http://www.linqpad.net/">LINQPad</a> via a comment on <a href="http://blog.wekeroad.com/2008/02/27/creating-in-queries-with-linq-to-sql/">Rob Conery's blog</a> (which I found <a href="http://www.dotnetkicks.com/linq/Creating_IN_queries_with_Linq">via DNK</a>). It's basically a code snippet IDE for C# 3.0 and VB9, with it also has built in database connection support, so it can fulfil much the same role as SQL Management Studio. I only played with it for a few minutes, but I was really impressed.  This is definitely going in my utilities folder. I wonder if they're interested in supporting F#? </li><li>Not sure how I missed this, but you can get <a href="http://windowsclient.net/apps/MsdnReaderSetup.exe">MSDN Magazine</a> via same Syndicated Client Experience as <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=dd466bbb-1b7d-438e-9f9a-954ce2058f15&amp;displaylang=en">Architecture Journal</a>. Unlike AJ which is divided into issues, the MSDN magazine client is divided into topics which is harder to square with the physical magazine. On the other hand, since MSDN Mag has been around longer, perhaps topics + search is a better discovery mechanism.  </li><li>Soma <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/somasegar/archive/2008/02/27/visual-studio-gallery.aspx">announces</a> the <a href="http://visualstudiogallery.com/">Visual Studio Gallery</a>, a repository of VS Extensions. It's kinda cool, but the whole discovery mechanism is clunky. I might like to experiment with some free or even free trial products, but there's no way to filter on cost so finding them is a hassle. Also, there's no way for community members to vote, rate or comment on the products in any way. </li><li>Nick Malik <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/nickmalik/archive/2008/02/23/enterprise-architecture-earning-our-keep.aspx">can't answer the question</a> "how does Enterprise Architecture demonstrate value?" I could be snarky and say "it doesn't", but that's only half the answer. It doesn't, but it should. My opinion, since you asked Nick, is that EA fails to deliver value because it tries to control the uncontrollable. Trying to gain efficiency thru establishing standards and eliminating overlap via reuse are pipe dreams, though literally millions of $$$ have been poured into those sink-holes. There are a few areas where centrally funded infrastructure projects can solve big problems that individual projects can't effectively tackle on their own. EA should focus their time there, they can actually make a difference. Otherwise, they should stay out of project's way.</li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
  <excerpt:encoded xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
  <wp:post_id xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">1109</wp:post_id>
  <wp:post_date xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2008-02-27 10:17:22</wp:post_date>
  <wp:post_date_gmt xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">2008-02-27 18:17:22</wp:post_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:comment_status>
  <wp:ping_status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">open</wp:ping_status>
  <wp:post_name xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">morning-coffee-150</wp:post_name>
  <wp:status xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">publish</wp:status>
  <wp:post_parent xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:post_parent>
  <wp:menu_order xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:menu_order>
  <wp:post_type xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">post</wp:post_type>
  <wp:post_password xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"></wp:post_password>
  <wp:is_sticky xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">0</wp:is_sticky>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="entertainment"><![CDATA[Entertainment]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="hockey"><![CDATA[Hockey]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="linq"><![CDATA[LINQ]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="microsoft"><![CDATA[Microsoft]]></category>
  <category domain="category" nicename="morning-coffee"><![CDATA[Morning Coffee]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="visual-studio"><![CDATA[Visual Studio]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="washington-capitals"><![CDATA[Washington Capitals]]></category>
  <category domain="post_tag" nicename="xml"><![CDATA[XML]]></category>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_entryid</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[5f0a893b-18d0-4e4c-9383-d53fb532b8f3]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitle</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Morning+Coffee+150]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>dasblog_compressedtitleunique</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2008/02/27/Morning+Coffee+150]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:postmeta xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
    <wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
  </wp:postmeta>
  <wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:comment_id>2034</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[ilanchelian]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email>ilanchelian@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>203.11.134.217</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2008-02-27 20:33:08</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2008-02-28 04:33:08</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[could you share with us some of .net related utilities that you use oftentimes.]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
  </wp:comment>
  <wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
    <wp:comment_id>2035</wp:comment_id>
    <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Nick Malik]]></wp:comment_author>
    <wp:comment_author_email></wp:comment_author_email>
    <wp:comment_author_url>http://blogs.msdn.com/nickmalik</wp:comment_author_url>
    <wp:comment_author_IP>131.107.0.102</wp:comment_author_IP>
    <wp:comment_date>2008-02-29 12:58:52</wp:comment_date>
    <wp:comment_date_gmt>2008-02-29 20:58:52</wp:comment_date_gmt>
    <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Hi Harry,

You implied that I could not answer the question, "How does EA demonstrate value."  That is not true.  I can readily answer the question, from my viewpoint, but I chose instead to *ask* the question to see if my answer matches the various answers that I may hear back.  I got a lot of valuable input, both on the blog and on the forum on Shared Insights where I asked the same question.

You are the ONLY person to reply and say that EA provides no value.  

Perhaps you should read about the role and value of Enterprise Architecture from established sources before you bash the entire profession.

EA is real, my friend.  It is as real as city planning.  The only major city in the US without city planning is Houston.  I have visited a few times, and I can honestly say that without city planning, they are a mess.  

http://www.architectureandgovernance.com/articles/12-evolving_role.asp

--- Nick]]></wp:comment_content>
    <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
    <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
    <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
    <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
  </wp:comment>
</item>