<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<wp:comment xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/">
  <wp:comment_id>2894</wp:comment_id>
  <wp:comment_author><![CDATA[CJ]]></wp:comment_author>
  <wp:comment_author_email>nospamplease@somewhere.com</wp:comment_author_email>
  <wp:comment_author_url></wp:comment_author_url>
  <wp:comment_author_IP>12.10.147.122</wp:comment_author_IP>
  <wp:comment_date>2006-02-15 11:23:52</wp:comment_date>
  <wp:comment_date_gmt>2006-02-15 19:23:52</wp:comment_date_gmt>
  <wp:comment_content><![CDATA[I don't watch Bill Maher because he strikes me as rather pompous, all politics aside.  

I remember Miller going after Reagan and Bush Sr. in the 80s -- not exactly the m.o. of a diehard Republican.  What changed?  Miller claims that his turning point was 9/11; if so, how can a man so previously "sharp witted" become such a dunce?

This sounds just like the charges leveled at Bush: he's a moron and a rube...but he's the most SINISTER and BRILLIANT simpleton in the world, who managed to lead a massive conspiracy to steal at least one U.S. election and lead the country into war.

Hey, you can't have it both ways.

And since we're on the topic of 9/11 and you mentioned Bush sitting in that classroom: what ELSE was he supposed to do?  Dive into a coat closet, throw on his Superman costume, and fly to the rescue?  Stand up, race out of the classroom and alarm the kids?  Or assume that the first reponders and the military are on it and that ten more minutes in a school won't change a thing?

What could have Bush done on that day that would have changed ANYTHING?

Kerry and Dean are easy targets for comedians like Miller: the former is a cold, robotic relic from the 60s who spends more time posing and talking about his few months in Vietnam than in the Senate, and the second is a delusional windbag who currently is spending more of the Democratic party's money than they can raise.

Steve is right: we're all more sensitive to jokes about things we hold dear.  But that doesn't mean we can't recognize our own partisan preferences and admit that the other side is right once in a while.]]></wp:comment_content>
  <wp:comment_approved>1</wp:comment_approved>
  <wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
  <wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
  <wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
</wp:comment>